Register of the Golitsyn family papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Golitsyn family papers
1904-1992
90027
Golitsyn family
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers consist of memoirs, writings, correspondence, identification documents, and certificates, relating to conditions in Russia prior to, during and after the Russian Revolution, and to Russian émigré life in Harbin, China, France, and the United States. Includes material relating to the Glebov family, as well as the papers of Mikhail Vladimirovich Golitsyn, Aleksandr Vladimirovich Golitsyn and Liubov' Vladimirovna Golitsyna.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note: Aleksandr Vladimirovich Golitsyn
1876 December 13 Born in Moscow, Russia, to an aristocratic family
1901 October 16 Received medical degree from Moscow University
1901 November 23 Married Liubov' Glebova (1883-1948)
1921-1923 Emigrated with his wife and children to Harbin, China where he worked as a doctor for the Russian Society of the Red Cross
1923 October 16 Arrived in Seattle from Harbin, China, and applied for U.S. citizenship
1924 January-1940s Received U.S. medical license and practiced medicine in Seattle and Los Angeles
1951 Died, Los Angeles, California
Biographical Note: Mikhail Vladimirovich Golitsyn
1873 September 2 Born in Moscow, Russia, to an aristocratic family
1892-1896 Studied law at Moscow University
1922?-1929 Worked for Gosplan, the Soviet state planning committee, until dismissed. Requested reinstatement and was denied
1931 Moved with his family to Dmitrov, Soviet Union
Late 1930s Wrote his memoirs of the pre-revolutionary period, Moi vospominaniia, 1873-1917, published in 2007 by Russkiĭ mir
1942 Died, Dmitrov
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist of memoirs, writings, correspondence, identification documents, and certificates, relating to conditions in Russia prior to, during and after the Russian Revolution, and to Russian émigré life in Harbin, China, France, and the United States. Includes material relating to the Glebov family, as well as the papers of Mikhail Vladimirovich Golitsyn, Aleksandr Vladimirovich Golitsyn and Liubov' Vladimirovna Golitsyna.
The bulk of the collection is comprised of correspondence among members of the Glebov and Golitsyn families. Writing to their daughter from exile in France, Sofiia and Vladimir Glebov's letters document Russian émigré life in western Europe, while the letters of Mikhail Vladimirovich Golitsyn to his brother Aleksandr describe conditions in Russia after the Bolshevik revolution. Of particular interest in the Correspondence series are letters from Nestor, the Archbishop of Kamchatka and Seoul, on Russian refugees in Harbin, China, and the Russian Orthodox Church in exile.
The Aleksandr Golitsyn Career Files relate to the Russian Society of the Red Cross's efforts to resettle the Russian refugees of Harbin in Canada. Memoranda and correspondence with Canadian officials and Serge Ughet, the financial attaché of the Russian embassy, document measures to secure visas and jobs for Russian immigrants on the Canadian Pacific railway. A report to the League of Nations describes the bleak conditions at orphanages for Russian refugee children in China.
Several memoirs by members of the Glebov and Golitsyn families are included in the Writings series. In "Intimate Days with Tolstoy," Sofiia Glebova recalls conversations with the writer Leo Tolstoy at Iasnaia Poliana after her daughter's marriage to Tolstoy's son. Memoirs by Mikhail Golitsyn and Vladimir Trubetskoĭ describe aristocratic life in Russia at the beginning of the 20th century. "Sudebnoe delo sem'i Vladimira Sergeevicha Trubetskogo" consists of assembled correspondence and reports on the fate of five members of the Trubetskoi family executed or sentenced to the gulag in 1937.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Russia--Social conditions.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--Social conditions.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; Glebov family.; Harbin (China); Golitsyn, Mikhail Vladimirovich, 1873-1942.; Golitsyn, Aleksandr Vladimirovich, 1876-; Golitsyna, Liubov' V., 1883-1948
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1917-1942; 1-2 (Box 1-2:)
  Consists of correspondence among members of the Glebov and Golitsyn families, primarily to Liubov' Golitsyna from her parents and to Aleksandr Golitsyn from his brother Mikhail. Divided into two subseries: general correspondence and Russian Orthodox Church correspondence. Arranged by correspondent and thereunder chronologically
  - General, 1917-1940
    - Gaiarin, Fedor, 1921 July 18 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Glebov family, 1917-1927, 1930-1931 and 1937
      Consists mainly of letters from Sofiia Nikolaevna Glebova (née Trubetskaia) and Vladimir Petrovich Glebov to their daughter Liubov'. Also includes correspondence from Glebov siblings and unidentified relatives
      - 1917-1920 (Folder 1: 2-6)
      - 1920 (Folder 1: 7-8)
      - 1921 (Folder 1: 9-12)
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 1: 13-16)
      - 1924 (Folder 1: 17-21)
      - 1925 (Folder 1: 22-30)
      - 1926-1927 (Folder 1: 31-35)
      - 1930-1931 (Folder 1: 36)
      - 1937 (Folder 1: 37)
    - Golitsyn family, 1917-1918, 1920-1930, 1940
      Consists mainly of letters from Mikhail Vladimirovich Golitsyn to his brother Aleksandr. Also includes correspondence from Aleksandr's parents, Vladimir Mikhaĭlovich Golitsyn and Sofiia Golitsyna
      - 1917 (Folder 1: 38)
      - 1918 (Folder 1: 39-42)
      - 1920 (Folder 1: 43)
      - 1921-1923 (Folder 1: 44-48)
      - 1924 (Folder 1: 49-51)
      - 1925-1926 (Folder 1: 52-54)
      - 1927-1930 (Folder 1: 55-57)
      - 1932 (Folder 1: 58-59)
      - 1933 (Folder 1: 60)
      - 1934 (Folder 1: 61)
      - 1935 (Folder 1: 62)
      - 1936 (Folder 1: 63)
      - 1937 (Folder 1: 64)
      - 1938 (Folder 1: 65)
      - 1939 (Folder 1: 66)
      - 1940 (Folder 1: 67)
      - undated (Folder 1: 68)
    - Harbin associates, 1924-1925 (Folder 2: 1-5)
    - Hester, C. Floyd, 1923 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Iarmokhovich, Mariia, 1924-1925 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Iarmolovich, Aleksandra, 1918-1924 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Russkiĭ golos, 1925 November 2 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Shelkovnikov, N., 1922 December 19 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Sturgis, Milton, 1928 January 17 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Ughet, Serge, financial attaché of the Russian Embassy in the U.S., 1923-1925 (Folder 2: 12-14)
    - Unidentified, 1917-1918, 1921-1925, 1927, 1932, 1933 and undated
    - 1917 (Folder 2: 15)
    - 1918 (Folder 2: 16-21)
    - 1921 (Folder 2: 22-26)
    - 1922 (Folder 2: 27-28)
    - 1923 (Folder 2: 29-31)
    - 1924 (Folder 2: 32)
    - 1925 (Folder 2: 33-38)
    - 1927 (Folder 2: 39-40)
    - 1932 (Folder 2: 41)
    - 1933 (Folder 2: 42)
    - undated (Folder 2: 43-45)
  - Russian Orthodox Church, 1922-1927 and 1942
    - Alexy, Bishop of San Francisco, 1927 June 1 (Folder 2: 46)
    - Baranoff, Makary, Rector of the Russian Orthodox Church of Juneau, Alaska, 1942 December 27 (Folder 2: 47)
    - Nestor, Archbishop of Kamchatka and Seoul (Nikolai Aleksandrovich Anisimov), Harbin, 1922-1926 (Folder 2: 48-54)
      Includes postcard with photograph of Nestor
    - Platon, Archbishop of New York, 1927 and undated (Folder 2: 55)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence related to the Russian Orthodox Church, 1922-1924 (Folder 2: 56-58)
- Golitsyn family files, 1911-1924; 3 (Box 3:)
  Contains certificates, receipts, school reports, ledgers, and visa applications by Liubov' and Aleksandr Golitsyn. Arranged chronologically
  - Financial ledger for Liubov' Golitsyna, 1911-1912 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Rental agreement and property insurance records, 1917 and 1923 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Donation to a soldiers' charity, 1917 August 5 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Safe conduct passes and certificates of employment for Liubov' and Aleksandr Golitsyn, 1917-1920 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Report cards for Ol'ga, Natalia, and Aleksandr Golitsyn, 1919 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Donation to a tuberculosis charity signed by Liubov' Golitsyna, 1920s (Folder 3: 6)
  - Grocery bill, 1920s (Folder 3: 7)
  - M.O. Vol'f bookstore account, 1922 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Affidavit of intent to become a United States citizen by Aleksandr Golitsyn, 1923 February 27 (Folder 3: 9)
  - United States visas for Liubov' and Aleksandr Golitsyn and children, 1924 January 22 and May 7 (Folder 3: 10)
    Includes photographs
- Aleksandr Vladimirovich Golitsyn career files, 1904-1928; 3 (Box 3:)
  Includes memoranda, correspondence, surveys, receipts, and notes related to Aleksandr Golitsyn's medical career and his work with refugees in Harbin for the Russian Society of the Red Cross. Arranged in three groups: Russia and United States career files, Russian Society of the Red Cross in China files, and Miscellany; and thereunder chronologically
  - Russia and United States career files, 1904-1928
    - Moscow State University medical diploma and certified copy in English and Russian, 1904 and 1927 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Salary rates chart, Tiumen', 1918 November 21 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Certificate of employment and correspondence, Tiumen' hospital, 1919 July (Folder 3: 13)
    - Orders to open a military depot in Tiumen' signed by General Mikhail Konstantinovich Diterikhs, 1919 July 19 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Budget ledger, 1920 January 1 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Certificate of employment, Irkutsk hospital and Harbin Medical School, 1920 and 1923 August 31 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Letters of reference by the Harbin hospital director and Milton Sturgis, 1923 September 7 and 1928 January 14 (Folder 3: 17)
    - United States medical license, 1924 January (Folder 3: 18)
  - Russian Society of the Red Cross in China files, 1920-1924
    - Certificate of employment, Russian Society of the Red Cross, 1920 November 24 and 1923 August 30 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Russian children's charity in Harbin donor list, circa 1922 (Folder 3: 20)
    - "Report to Dr. Greig, Representative of the League of Nations, on the Position of Russian Refugee Children in Harbin,", circa 1923 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Russian immigrants to China by occupation survey, circa 1923 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Memoranda, 1923-1924
      - "Authorization for Aleksandr Golitsyn to Negotiate with the Canadian government on Behalf of Russian Refugees,", 1923 (Folder 3: 23)
      - "On Questions to be Cleared up with Proper Canadian Authorities and Institutions in Regard to Possible Transportation of Russian Refugees from Manchuria to Canada,", circa 1923 (Folder 3: 24)
      - "To Canadian Immigration Authorities in Regard to Possible Absorption by Canada of Part of Russian Refugees from Manchuria,", 1924 January 31 (Folder 3: 25)
    - Correspondence, 1923-1924
      On settling Russian refugees in Canada
      - Serge Ughet to S.S. Aksakov, 1923 September 7 (Folder 3: 26)
      - General, 1924 January-February (Folder 3: 27)
      - Canadian Pacific Railway Correspondence, Department of Colonization and Development, 1924 February 15 (Folder 3: 28)
        Relates to employing Russian refugees on railroad construction projects
  - Miscellany, 1918-1928
    - Notes, 1918-1928 (Folder 3: 29)
    - Obshchestvo sodeĭstviia torgovo-promyshlennomu razvitiiu Rossii donation receipt, 1918 March (Folder 3: 30)
    - Harbin Club calling card and invitation, 1922 (Folder 3: 31)
    - Russian Orthodox Church flyers and clipping, 1922 (Folder 3: 32)
    - Patriarkh Tikhon death announcement, 1923 (Folder 3: 33)
    - Kruzhok Revniteleĭ Pravoslavii donation receipts and correspondence, 1924 February (Folder 3: 34)
- Writings, 1923-1992 and undated; 3-4 (Box 3-4:)
  Consists of memoirs, published and unpublished writings, and notes relating to pre-Revolutionary Russia, Leo Tolstoy, the Russian Orthodox Church and the Stalin era. Arranged in two groups: By author and Author unknown, and thereunder alphabetically
  - By author, 1923-1925, 1930s, 1990 and undated
    - Dakserhof, Marina, assorted notes, circa 1990 (Folder 3: 35)
    - Gleboff, Sophie, "Intimate Days with Tolstoy," translated by Lewis Stanton Palen, typescript with corrections, Paris, 1924 (Folder 3: 36)
      Gleboff describes her visits with the writer Leo Tolstoy after her daughter Aleksandra's marriage to Tolstoy's son Mikhail
    - Golitsyn, Aleksandr Mikhaĭlovich, Pamiatnyia zapiski Kniazia Aleksandra Mikhaĭlovicha Golitsyna, typescript, undated (Folder 3: 37)
    - Golitsyn, Mikhail Vladimirovich, Moi vospominaniia, 1873-1917, photocopy of typescript, 1930s (Folder 4: 1-6)
    - Nestor, Archbishop of Kamchatka and Seoul (Nikolai Aleksandrovich Anisimov), religious writings, 1923-1925 and undated (Folder 4: 7-10)
      Consists of tracts by Nestor on religious holidays and profiles of Patriarkh Tikhon and Arkhiepiskop Nikolai Iaponskiĭ
    - Tolstaia, Aleksandra Vladimirovna (née Glebova), Barykovka, 1942 December 17 (Folder 4: 11)
      Tolstaia's memoirs of her childhood at the Glebov family estate, Barykovka
    - Trubetskoĭ, Vladimir Sergeevich, Zapiski Kirasira, undated (Folder 4: 12-13)
      Relates to the Russian Imperial Kirasir Household Troops Regiment of Her Majesty Mariia Feodorovna during the period 1911-1913
    - Zagorskiĭ, M., "Patriarkh Tikhon,", 1925 June 27 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Author unknown, 1992 June 21 and undated
    - Fragment, undated (Folder 4: 15)
      One typescript page with corrections in English
    - "Kontorshchik Vznuzdaev," manuscript fragment, undated (Folder 4: 16)
    - "Sudebnoe delo sem'i Vladimira Sergeevicha Trubetskogo,", 1992 June 21 (Folder 4: 17)
      Relates to the rehabilitation of several members of the Trubetskoĭ family, including Vladimir Sergeevich (1891-1937) and Varvara Vladimirovna (1917-1937), both executed by the NKVD in Andizhan. Two other Trubetskoĭ family members, Grigoriĭ Vladmirovich and Aleksandra Vladimirovna, were sentenced to the gulag in 1937 for counterrevolutionary activities